<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://enigma.github.io/pgrss/rss-2022-11.xml</id>
  <title>Paul Graham's Essays</title>
  <updated>2022-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <link href="https://paulgraham.com/" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://enigma.github.io/pgrss/rss-2022-11.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
  <link href="https://enigma.github.io/pgrss/rss-2004-11.xml" rel="first" type="application/rss+xml"/>
  <link href="https://enigma.github.io/pgrss/rss-2020-01.xml" rel="previous" type="application/rss+xml"/>
  <link href="https://enigma.github.io/pgrss/rss.xml" rel="next" type="application/rss+xml"/>
  <link href="https://enigma.github.io/pgrss/rss.xml" rel="last" type="application/rss+xml"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="1.0.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <subtitle>Paul Graham's Essays</subtitle>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//read.html</id>
    <title>The Need to Read</title>
    <updated>2026-01-26T12:01:01.779550+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;November 2022&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In the science fiction books I read as a kid, reading had often
been replaced by some more efficient way of acquiring knowledge.
Mysterious "tapes" would load it into one's brain like a program
being loaded into a computer.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;That sort of thing is unlikely to happen anytime soon. Not just
because it would be hard to build a replacement for reading, but
because even if one existed, it would be insufficient. Reading about
x doesn't just t&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//read.html"/>
    <published>2022-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//want.html</id>
    <title>What You (Want to)* Want</title>
    <updated>2026-01-26T12:01:01.778314+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;November 2022&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Since I was about 9 I've been puzzled by the apparent contradiction
between being made of matter that behaves in a predictable way, and
the feeling that I could choose to do whatever I wanted. At the
time I had a self-interested motive for exploring the question. At
that age (like most succeeding ages) I was always in trouble with
the authorities, and it seemed to me that there might possibly be
some way to get out of trouble by arguing that I&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//want.html"/>
    <published>2022-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//alien.html</id>
    <title>Alien Truth</title>
    <updated>2026-01-26T12:01:01.777200+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;October 2022&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If there were intelligent beings elsewhere in the universe, they'd
share certain truths in common with us. The truths of mathematics
would be the same, because they're true by definition. Ditto for
the truths of physics; the mass of a carbon atom would be the same
on their planet. But I think we'd share other truths with aliens
besides the truths of math and physics, and that it would be
worthwhile to think about what these might be.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;F&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//alien.html"/>
    <published>2022-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//users.html</id>
    <title>What I've Learned from Users</title>
    <updated>2026-01-26T12:01:01.774313+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;September 2022&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;I recently told applicants to Y Combinator that the best advice I
could give for getting in, per word, was 
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  Explain what you've learned from users.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
That tests a lot of things: whether you're paying attention to
users, how well you understand them, and even how much they need
what you're making.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Afterward I asked myself the same question. What have I learned
from YC's users, the startups we've funded?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//users.html"/>
    <published>2022-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//heresy.html</id>
    <title>Heresy</title>
    <updated>2026-01-26T12:01:01.771314+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;April 2022&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;One of the most surprising things I've witnessed in my lifetime is
the rebirth of the concept of heresy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In his excellent biography of Newton, Richard Westfall writes about the
moment when he was elected a fellow of Trinity College:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  Supported comfortably, Newton was free to devote himself wholly
  to whatever he chose. To remain on, he had only to avoid the three
  unforgivable sins: crime, heresy, and marriage.
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//heresy.html"/>
    <published>2022-04-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//words.html</id>
    <title>Putting Ideas into Words</title>
    <updated>2026-01-26T12:01:01.769615+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;February 2022&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Writing about something, even something you know well, usually shows
you that you didn't know it as well as you thought. Putting ideas
into words is a severe test. The first words you choose are usually
wrong; you have to rewrite sentences over and over &lt;!-- if you want --&gt; to
get them exactly right. And your ideas won't just be imprecise, but
incomplete too. Half the ideas that end up in an essay will be ones
you thought of while you were wri&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//words.html"/>
    <published>2022-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//goodtaste.html</id>
    <title>Is There Such a Thing as Good Taste?</title>
    <updated>2026-01-26T12:01:01.768120+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;November 2021&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;i&gt;(This essay is derived from a talk at the Cambridge Union.)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;When I was a kid, I'd have said there wasn't. My father told me so.
Some people like some things, and other people like other things,
and who's to say who's right?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;It seemed so obvious that there was no such thing as good taste
that it was only through indirect evidence that I realized my father
was wrong. And that's what I'm going to give you here: a proof by&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//goodtaste.html"/>
    <published>2021-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//smart.html</id>
    <title>Beyond Smart</title>
    <updated>2026-01-26T12:01:01.765789+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;October 2021&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If you asked people what was special about Einstein, most would say
that he was really smart. Even the ones who tried to give you a
more sophisticated-sounding answer would probably think this first.
Till a few years ago I would have given the same answer myself. But
that wasn't what was special about Einstein. What was special about
him was that he had important new ideas. Being very smart was a
necessary precondition for having those ideas, b&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//smart.html"/>
    <published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//weird.html</id>
    <title>Weird Languages</title>
    <updated>2026-01-26T12:01:01.765050+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;August 2021&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;When people say that in their experience all programming languages
are basically equivalent, they're making a statement not about
languages but about the kind of programming they've done.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;99.5% of programming consists of gluing together calls to library
functions. All popular languages are equally good at this. So one
can easily spend one's whole career operating in the intersection
of popular programming languages.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;But the oth&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//weird.html"/>
    <published>2021-08-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//hwh.html</id>
    <title>How to Work Hard</title>
    <updated>2026-01-26T12:01:01.761030+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;June 2021&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;It might not seem there's much to learn about how to work hard.
Anyone who's been to school knows what it entails, even if they
chose not to do it. There are 12 year olds who work amazingly hard. And
yet when I ask if I know more about working hard now than when I
was in school, the answer is definitely yes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;One thing I know is that if you want to do great things, you'll
have to work very hard. I wasn't sure of that as a kid. Schoolwork
v&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//hwh.html"/>
    <published>2021-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//own.html</id>
    <title>A Project of One's Own</title>
    <updated>2026-01-26T12:01:01.758053+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;June 2021&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A few days ago, on the way home from school, my nine year old son
told me he couldn't wait to get home to write more of the story he
was working on. This made me as happy as anything I've heard him
say — not just because he was excited about his story, but because
he'd discovered this way of working. Working on a project of your
own is as different from ordinary work as skating is from walking.
It's more fun, but also much more productive.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//own.html"/>
    <published>2021-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//fn.html</id>
    <title>Fierce Nerds</title>
    <updated>2026-01-26T12:01:01.756014+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;May 2021&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Most people think of nerds as quiet, diffident people. In ordinary
social situations they are — as quiet and diffident as the star
quarterback would be if he found himself in the middle of a physics
symposium. And for the same reason: they are fish out of water.
But the apparent diffidence of nerds is an illusion due to the fact
that when non-nerds observe them, it's usually in ordinary social
situations. In fact some nerds are quite fierce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//fn.html"/>
    <published>2021-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//newideas.html</id>
    <title>Crazy New Ideas</title>
    <updated>2026-01-26T12:01:01.753671+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;May 2021&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There's one kind of opinion I'd be very afraid to express publicly.
If someone I knew to be both a domain expert and a reasonable person
proposed an idea that sounded preposterous, I'd be very reluctant
to say "That will never work."&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Anyone who has studied the history of ideas, and especially the
history of science, knows that's how big things start. Someone
proposes an idea that sounds crazy, most people dismiss it, then
it gradually take&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//newideas.html"/>
    <published>2021-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//nft.html</id>
    <title>An NFT That Saves Lives</title>
    <updated>2026-01-26T12:01:01.752824+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;May 2021&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.noorahealth.org/"&gt;Noora Health&lt;/a&gt;, a nonprofit I've 
supported for years, just launched
a new NFT. It has a dramatic name, &lt;a href="http://bit.ly/NooraNFT"&gt;&lt;u&gt;Save Thousands of Lives&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
because that's what the proceeds will do.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Noora has been saving lives for 7 years. They run programs in
hospitals in South Asia to teach new mothers how to take care of
their babies once they get home. They're in 165 hospitals no&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//nft.html"/>
    <published>2021-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//real.html</id>
    <title>The Real Reason to End the Death Penalty</title>
    <updated>2026-01-26T12:01:01.751603+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;April 2021&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;When intellectuals talk about the death penalty, they talk about
things like whether it's permissible for the state to take someone's
life, whether the death penalty acts as a deterrent, and whether
more death sentences are given to some groups than others. But in
practice the debate about the death penalty is not about whether
it's ok to kill murderers. It's about whether it's ok to kill
innocent people, because at least 4% of people on death ro&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//real.html"/>
    <published>2021-04-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//richnow.html</id>
    <title>How People Get Rich Now</title>
    <updated>2026-01-26T12:01:01.747505+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;April 2021&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Every year since 1982, &lt;i&gt;Forbes&lt;/i&gt; magazine has published a list of the&#13;
richest Americans. If we compare the 100 richest people in 1982 to&#13;
the 100 richest in 2020, we notice some big differences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In 1982 the most common source of wealth was inheritance. Of the&#13;
100 richest people, 60 inherited from an ancestor. There were 10&#13;
du Pont heirs alone. By 2020 the number of heirs had been cut in&#13;
half, accounting for only 27 of the biggest&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//richnow.html"/>
    <published>2021-04-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//simply.html</id>
    <title>Write Simply</title>
    <updated>2026-01-26T12:01:01.746559+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;March 2021&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;I try to write using ordinary words and simple sentences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;That kind of writing is easier to read, and the easier something
is to read, the more deeply readers will engage with it. The less
energy they expend on your prose, the more they'll have left for
your ideas.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;And the further they'll read. Most readers' energy tends to flag
part way through an article or essay. If the friction of reading
is low enough, more keep going till &lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//simply.html"/>
    <published>2021-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//donate.html</id>
    <title>Donate Unrestricted</title>
    <updated>2026-01-26T12:01:01.745542+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;March 2021&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The secret curse of the nonprofit world is restricted donations.
If you haven't been involved with nonprofits, you may never have
heard this phrase before. But if you have been, it probably made
you wince.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Restricted donations mean donations where the donor limits what can
be done with the money. This is common with big donations, perhaps
the default. And yet it's usually a bad idea. Usually the way the
donor wants the money spent is not&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//donate.html"/>
    <published>2021-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//worked.html</id>
    <title>What I Worked On</title>
    <updated>2026-01-26T12:01:01.733799+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;February 2021&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Before college the two main things I worked on, outside of school,
were writing and programming. I didn't write essays. I wrote what
beginning writers were supposed to write then, and probably still
are: short stories. My stories were awful. They had hardly any plot,
just characters with strong feelings, which I imagined made them
deep.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The first programs I tried writing were on the IBM 1401 that our
school district used for what was &lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//worked.html"/>
    <published>2021-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//earnest.html</id>
    <title>Earnestness</title>
    <updated>2026-01-26T12:01:01.730772+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;December 2020&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Jessica and I have certain words that have special significance
when we're talking about startups. The highest compliment we can
pay to founders is to describe them as "earnest." This is not by
itself a guarantee of success. You could be earnest but incapable.
But when founders are both formidable (another of our words) and
earnest, they're as close to unstoppable as you get.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Earnestness sounds like a boring, even Victorian virtue. It&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//earnest.html"/>
    <published>2020-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//ace.html</id>
    <title>Billionaires Build</title>
    <updated>2026-01-26T12:01:01.727511+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;December 2020&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As I was deciding what to write about next, I was surprised to find
that two separate essays I'd been planning to write were actually
the same.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The first is about how to ace your Y Combinator interview. There
has been so much nonsense written about this topic that I've been
meaning for years to write something telling founders the truth.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The second is about something politicians sometimes say  that the
only way to become a b&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//ace.html"/>
    <published>2020-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//airbnbs.html</id>
    <title>The Airbnbs</title>
    <updated>2026-01-26T12:01:01.726417+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;December 2020&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To celebrate Airbnb's IPO and to help future founders, I thought
it might be useful to explain what was special about Airbnb.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;What was special about the Airbnbs was how earnest they were. They
did nothing half-way, and we could sense this even in the interview.
Sometimes after we interviewed a startup we'd be uncertain what to
do, and have to talk it over. Other times we'd just look at one
another and smile. The Airbnbs' interview was&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//airbnbs.html"/>
    <published>2020-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//think.html</id>
    <title>How to Think for Yourself</title>
    <updated>2026-01-26T12:01:01.721694+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;November 2020&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There are some kinds of work that you can't do well without thinking
differently from your peers. To be a successful scientist, for
example, it's not enough just to be correct. Your ideas have to be
both correct and novel. You can't publish papers saying things other
people already know. You need to say things no one else has realized
yet.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The same is true for investors. It's not enough for a public market
investor to predict correctl&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//think.html"/>
    <published>2020-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//early.html</id>
    <title>Early Work</title>
    <updated>2026-01-26T12:01:01.718177+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;October 2020&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;One of the biggest things holding people back from doing great work
is the fear of making something lame. And this fear is not an
irrational one. Many great projects go through a stage early on
where they don't seem very impressive, even to their creators. You
have to push through this stage to reach the great work that lies
beyond. But many people don't. Most people don't even reach the
stage of making something they're embarrassed by, let alo&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//early.html"/>
    <published>2020-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//wtax.html</id>
    <title>Modeling a Wealth Tax</title>
    <updated>2026-01-26T12:01:01.715024+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;August 2020&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Some politicians are proposing to introduce wealth taxes in addition
to income and capital gains taxes. Let's try modeling the effects of various levels
of wealth tax to see what they would mean in practice for a startup
founder.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Suppose you start a successful startup in your twenties, and then
live for another 60 years. How much of your stock will a wealth tax
consume?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If the wealth tax applies to all your assets, it's easy to&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//wtax.html"/>
    <published>2020-08-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//conformism.html</id>
    <title>The Four Quadrants of Conformism</title>
    <updated>2026-01-26T12:01:01.712272+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;July 2020&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;One of the most revealing ways to classify people is by the degree
and aggressiveness of their conformism. Imagine a Cartesian coordinate
system whose horizontal axis runs from conventional-minded on the
left to independent-minded on the right, and whose vertical axis
runs from passive at the bottom to aggressive at the top. The
resulting four quadrants define four types of people. Starting in
the upper left and going counter-clockwise: aggressive&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//conformism.html"/>
    <published>2020-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//orth.html</id>
    <title>Orthodox Privilege</title>
    <updated>2026-01-26T12:01:01.710718+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;July 2020&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;table cellpadding="6" cellspacing="0" width="100%"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td bgcolor="#ffffdd"&gt;
&lt;table cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" width="100%"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td bgcolor="#ffffdd"&gt;&lt;font size="2"&gt;&#13;
"Few people are capable of expressing with equanimity opinions which differ from the prejudices of their social environment. Most people are even incapable of forming such opinions."&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; Einstein&#13;
&lt;/font&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
There has been &lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//orth.html"/>
    <published>2020-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//cred.html</id>
    <title>Coronavirus and Credibility</title>
    <updated>2026-01-26T12:01:01.710018+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;April 2020&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;I recently saw a 
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NAh4uS4f78o"&gt;&lt;u&gt;video&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; 
of TV journalists and politicians confidently
saying that the coronavirus would be no worse than the flu. What
struck me about it was not just how mistaken they seemed, but how
daring. How could they feel safe saying such things?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The answer, I realized, is that they didn't think they could get
caught. They didn't realize there was any danger in maki&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//cred.html"/>
    <published>2020-04-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//useful.html</id>
    <title>How to Write Usefully</title>
    <updated>2026-01-26T12:01:01.707210+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;February 2020&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;What should an essay be? Many people would say persuasive. That's
what a lot of us were taught essays should be. But I think we can
aim for something more ambitious: that an essay should be useful.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To start with, that means it should be correct. But it's not enough
merely to be correct. It's easy to make a statement correct by
making it vague. That's a common flaw in academic writing, for
example. If you know nothing at all about an i&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//useful.html"/>
    <published>2020-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//noob.html</id>
    <title>Being a Noob</title>
    <updated>2026-01-26T12:01:01.706377+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;January 2020&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;When I was young, I thought old people had everything figured out.
Now that I'm old, I know this isn't true.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;I constantly feel like a noob. It seems like I'm always talking to
some startup working in a new field I know nothing about, or reading
a book about a topic I don't understand well enough, or visiting some new
country where I don't know how things work.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;It's not pleasant to feel like a noob. And the word "noob" is
certa&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//noob.html"/>
    <published>2020-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
