<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://enigma.github.io/pgrss/rss-2020-01.xml</id>
  <title>Paul Graham's Essays</title>
  <updated>2020-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <link href="https://paulgraham.com/" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://enigma.github.io/pgrss/rss-2020-01.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
  <link href="https://enigma.github.io/pgrss/rss-2004-11.xml" rel="first" type="application/rss+xml"/>
  <link href="https://enigma.github.io/pgrss/rss-2013-09.xml" rel="previous" type="application/rss+xml"/>
  <link href="https://enigma.github.io/pgrss/rss-2022-11.xml" rel="next" type="application/rss+xml"/>
  <link href="https://enigma.github.io/pgrss/rss.xml" rel="last" type="application/rss+xml"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="1.0.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <subtitle>Paul Graham's Essays</subtitle>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//fh.html</id>
    <title>Haters</title>
    <updated>2026-02-03T00:03:48.527040+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;January 2020&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;i&gt;(I originally intended this for startup founders, who are often
surprised by the attention they get as their companies grow, but
it applies equally to anyone who becomes famous.)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If you become sufficiently famous, you'll acquire some fans who
like you too much. These people are sometimes called "fanboys," and
though I dislike that term, I'm going to have to use it here.  We
need some word for them, because this is a distinct phe&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//fh.html"/>
    <published>2020-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//mod.html</id>
    <title>The Two Kinds of Moderate</title>
    <updated>2026-02-03T00:03:48.526037+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;December 2019&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There are two distinct ways to be politically moderate: on purpose
and by accident. Intentional moderates are trimmers, deliberately
choosing a position mid-way between the extremes of right and left.
Accidental moderates end up in the middle, on average, because they
make up their own minds about each question, and the far right and
far left are roughly equally wrong.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;You can distinguish intentional from accidental moderates by the
d&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//mod.html"/>
    <published>2019-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//fp.html</id>
    <title>Fashionable Problems</title>
    <updated>2026-02-03T00:03:48.525445+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;December 2019&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;I've seen the same pattern in many different fields: even though
lots of people have worked hard in the field, only a small fraction
of the space of possibilities has been explored, because they've
all worked on similar things.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Even the smartest, most imaginative people are surprisingly
conservative when deciding what to work on. People who would never
dream of being fashionable in any other way get sucked into working
on fashionable &lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//fp.html"/>
    <published>2019-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//kids.html</id>
    <title>Having Kids</title>
    <updated>2026-02-03T00:03:48.523892+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;December 2019&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Before I had kids, I was afraid of having kids. Up to that point I
felt about kids the way the young Augustine felt about living
virtuously. I'd have been sad to think I'd never have children.
But did I want them now? No.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If I had kids, I'd become a parent, and parents, as I'd known since
I was a kid, were uncool. They were dull and responsible and had
no fun.  And while it's not surprising that kids would believe that,
to be honest I&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//kids.html"/>
    <published>2019-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//lesson.html</id>
    <title>The Lesson to Unlearn</title>
    <updated>2026-02-03T00:03:48.520924+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;December 2019&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
The most damaging thing you learned in school wasn't something you
learned in any specific class. It was learning to get good grades.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;When I was in college, a particularly earnest philosophy grad student
once told me that he never cared what grade he got in a class, only
what he learned in it. This stuck in my mind because it was the
only time I ever heard anyone say such a thing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;For me, as for most students, the measuremen&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//lesson.html"/>
    <published>2019-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//nov.html</id>
    <title>Novelty and Heresy</title>
    <updated>2026-02-03T00:03:48.520278+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;November 2019&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If you discover something new, there's a significant chance you'll be
accused of some form of heresy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To discover new things, you have
to work on ideas that are good but non-obvious; if an idea is
obviously good, other people are probably already working on it.
One common way for a good idea to be non-obvious is for it to be hidden in the
shadow of some mistaken assumption that people are very attached to.
But anything you discover fr&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//nov.html"/>
    <published>2019-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//genius.html</id>
    <title>The Bus Ticket Theory of Genius</title>
    <updated>2026-02-03T00:03:48.517591+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;November 2019&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Everyone knows that to do great work you need both natural ability
and determination. But there's a third ingredient that's not as
well understood: an obsessive interest in a particular topic.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To explain this point I need to burn my reputation with some group
of people, and I'm going to choose bus ticket collectors.  There
are people who collect old bus tickets. Like many collectors, they
have an obsessive interest in the minutiae of &lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//genius.html"/>
    <published>2019-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//sun.html</id>
    <title>General and Surprising</title>
    <updated>2026-02-03T00:03:48.516778+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;September 2017&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The most valuable insights are both general and surprising. 
F = ma for example. But general and surprising is a hard
combination to achieve. That territory tends to be picked
clean, precisely because those insights are so valuable.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Ordinarily, the best that people can do is one without the
other: either surprising without being general (e.g.
gossip), or general without being surprising (e.g.
platitudes).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Where things get in&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//sun.html"/>
    <published>2017-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//pow.html</id>
    <title>Charisma / Power</title>
    <updated>2026-02-03T00:03:48.516370+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;January 2017&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;People who are powerful but uncharismatic will tend to be disliked.
Their power makes them a target for criticism that they don't have
the charisma to disarm. That was Hillary Clinton's problem. It also
tends to be a problem for any CEO who is more of a builder than a
schmoozer. And yet the builder-type CEO is (like Hillary) probably
the best person for the job.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;I don't think there is any solution to this problem. It's human
nature. Th&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//pow.html"/>
    <published>2017-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//disc.html</id>
    <title>The Risk of Discovery</title>
    <updated>2026-02-03T00:03:48.515827+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;January 2017&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Because biographies of famous scientists tend to 
edit out their mistakes, we underestimate the 
degree of risk they were willing to take.
And because anything a famous scientist did that
wasn't a mistake has probably now become the
conventional wisdom, those choices don't
seem risky either.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Biographies of Newton, for example, understandably focus
more on physics than alchemy or theology.
The impression we get is that his unerring judg&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//disc.html"/>
    <published>2017-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//pgh.html</id>
    <title>How to Make Pittsburgh a Startup Hub</title>
    <updated>2026-02-03T00:03:48.513919+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;April 2016&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;i&gt;(This is a talk I gave at an event called Opt412 in Pittsburgh.
Much of it will apply to other towns.  But not all, because
as I say in the talk, Pittsburgh has some important advantages over
most would-be startup hubs.)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;What would it take to make Pittsburgh into a startup hub, like
Silicon Valley?  I understand Pittsburgh pretty well,
because I grew up here, in Monroeville. And I understand Silicon
Valley pretty well because that&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//pgh.html"/>
    <published>2016-04-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//vb.html</id>
    <title>Life is Short</title>
    <updated>2026-02-03T00:03:48.512060+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;January 2016&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Life is short, as everyone knows. When I was a kid I used to wonder
about this. Is life actually short, or are we really complaining
about its finiteness?  Would we be just as likely to feel life was
short if we lived 10 times as long?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Since there didn't seem any way to answer this question, I stopped
wondering about it.  Then I had kids.  That gave me a way to answer
the question, and the answer is that life actually is short.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//vb.html"/>
    <published>2016-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//ineq.html</id>
    <title>Economic Inequality</title>
    <updated>2026-02-03T00:03:48.507247+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;&lt;!-- &lt;table width=100% cellspacing=0&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td bgcolor=#ffeeaa&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.virtumundo.com/images/spacer.gif"
height=15 width=1&gt;&lt;font size=2&gt;
&lt;xb&gt;There is also a&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;a href="sim.html"&gt;&lt;u&gt;shorter version&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/font&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.virtumundo.com/images/spacer.gif" height=5 width=1&gt;&lt;/td
&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt; --&gt;
January 2016&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Since the 1970s, economic inequality in the US has increased
dramatically. And in particular, the rich have gotten &lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//ineq.html"/>
    <published>2016-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//re.html</id>
    <title>The Refragmentation</title>
    <updated>2026-02-03T00:03:48.497963+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;January 2016&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;One advantage of being old is that you can see change happen in
your lifetime.  A lot of the change I've seen is fragmentation.  US
politics is much more polarized than it used to be.  Culturally we
have ever less common ground. The creative class flocks to a handful
of happy cities, abandoning the rest.  And increasing economic
inequality means the spread between rich and poor is growing too.
I'd like to propose a hypothesis: that all these tr&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//re.html"/>
    <published>2016-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//jessica.html</id>
    <title>Jessica Livingston</title>
    <updated>2026-02-03T00:03:48.495823+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;November 2015&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A few months ago an article about Y Combinator said that early on
it had been a "one-man show."  It's sadly common to read that sort
of thing.  But the problem with that description is not just that
it's unfair.  It's also misleading.  Much of what's most novel about
YC is due to Jessica Livingston.  If you don't understand her, you
don't understand YC.  So let me tell you a little about Jessica.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;YC had 4 founders.  Jessica and I deci&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//jessica.html"/>
    <published>2015-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//bias.html</id>
    <title>A Way to Detect Bias</title>
    <updated>2026-02-03T00:03:48.494580+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;October 2015&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This will come as a surprise to a lot of people, but in some cases
it's possible to detect bias in a selection process without knowing
anything about the applicant pool.  Which is exciting because among
other things it means third parties can use this technique to detect
bias whether those doing the selecting want them to or not.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;You can use this technique whenever (a) you have at least
a random sample of the applicants that were selec&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//bias.html"/>
    <published>2015-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//talk.html</id>
    <title>Write Like You Talk</title>
    <updated>2026-02-03T00:03:48.493218+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;October 2015&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Here's a simple trick for getting more people to read what you
write: write in spoken language.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Something comes over most people when they start writing. They write
in a different language than they'd use if they were talking to a
friend. The sentence structure and even the words are different.
No one uses "pen" as a verb in spoken English. You'd feel like an
idiot using "pen" instead of "write" in a conversation with a friend.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//talk.html"/>
    <published>2015-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//aord.html</id>
    <title>Default Alive or Default Dead?</title>
    <updated>2026-02-03T00:03:48.491037+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;October 2015&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;When I talk to a startup that's been operating for more than 8 or
9 months, the first thing I want to know is almost always the same.
Assuming their expenses remain constant and their revenue growth
is what it has been over the last several months, do they make it to
profitability on the money they have left?  Or to put it more
dramatically, by default do they live or die?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The startling thing is how often the founders themselves don't &lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//aord.html"/>
    <published>2015-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//safe.html</id>
    <title>Why It's Safe for Founders to Be Nice</title>
    <updated>2026-02-03T00:03:48.489442+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;August 2015&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;I recently got an email from a founder that helped me understand
something important: why it's safe for startup founders to be nice
people.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;I grew up with a cartoon idea of a very successful businessman (in
the cartoon it was always a man): a rapacious, cigar-smoking,
table-thumping guy in his fifties who wins by exercising power, and
isn't too fussy about how.  As I've written before, one of
the things that has surprised me most about &lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//safe.html"/>
    <published>2015-08-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//name.html</id>
    <title>Change Your Name</title>
    <updated>2026-02-03T00:03:48.487841+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;August 2015&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If you have a US startup called X and you don't have x.com, you
should probably change your name.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The reason is not just that people can't find you.  For companies
with mobile apps, especially, having the right domain name is not
as critical as it used to be for getting users.  The problem with
not having the .com of your name is that it signals weakness.  Unless
you're so big that your reputation precedes you, a marginal domain
suggest&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//name.html"/>
    <published>2015-08-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//altair.html</id>
    <title>What Microsoft Is this the Altair Basic of?</title>
    <updated>2026-02-03T00:03:48.487240+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;February 2015&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;One of the most valuable exercises you can try if you want to
understand startups is to look at the most successful companies and
explain why they were not as lame as they seemed when they first
launched.  Because they practically all seemed lame at first. Not
just small, lame.  Not just the first step up a big mountain.  More
like the first step into a swamp.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A Basic interpreter for the Altair?  How could that ever grow into
a giant &lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//altair.html"/>
    <published>2015-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//ronco.html</id>
    <title>The Ronco Principle</title>
    <updated>2026-02-03T00:03:48.485860+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;January 2015&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;No one, VC or angel, has invested in more of the top startups than
Ron Conway.  He knows what happened in every deal in the Valley,
half the time because he arranged it.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;And yet he's a super nice guy.  In fact, nice is not the word.
Ronco is good. I know of zero instances in which he has behaved
badly.  It's hard even to imagine.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;When I first came to Silicon Valley I thought "How lucky that someone
so powerful is so benevolent&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//ronco.html"/>
    <published>2015-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//work.html</id>
    <title>What Doesn't Seem Like Work?</title>
    <updated>2026-02-03T00:03:48.484679+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;January 2015&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;My father is a mathematician. For most of my childhood he worked
for Westinghouse, modelling nuclear reactors.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;He was one of those lucky people who know early on what they want to
do.  When you talk to him about his childhood, there's a clear
watershed at about age 12, when he "got interested in maths."&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;He
grew up in the small Welsh seacoast town of &lt;a href="https://goo.gl/maps/rkzUm"&gt;Pwllheli&lt;/a&gt;.  As we retraced
his walk to &lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//work.html"/>
    <published>2015-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//corpdev.html</id>
    <title>Don't Talk to Corp Dev</title>
    <updated>2026-02-03T00:03:48.482828+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;January 2015&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Corporate Development, aka corp dev, is the group within companies
that buys other companies. If you're talking to someone from corp
dev, that's why, whether you realize it yet or not.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;It's usually a mistake to talk to corp dev unless (a) you want to
sell your company right now and (b) you're sufficiently likely to
get an offer at an acceptable price.  In practice that means startups
should only talk to corp dev when they're either doi&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//corpdev.html"/>
    <published>2015-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//95.html</id>
    <title>Let the Other 95% of Great Programmers In</title>
    <updated>2026-02-03T00:03:48.481271+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;December 2014&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;American technology companies want the government to make immigration
easier because they say they can't find enough programmers in the
US.  Anti-immigration people say that instead of letting foreigners
take these jobs, we should train more Americans to be programmers.
Who's right?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The technology companies are right. What the anti-immigration people
don't understand is that there is a huge variation in ability between
competent progr&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//95.html"/>
    <published>2014-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//ecw.html</id>
    <title>How to Be an Expert in a Changing World</title>
    <updated>2026-02-03T00:03:48.479498+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;December 2014&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If the world were static, we could have monotonically increasing
confidence in our beliefs.  The more (and more varied) experience
a belief survived, the less likely it would be false.  Most people
implicitly believe something like this about their opinions.  And
they're justified in doing so with opinions about things that don't
change much, like human nature.  But you can't trust your opinions
in the same way about things that change, which &lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//ecw.html"/>
    <published>2014-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//know.html</id>
    <title>How You Know</title>
    <updated>2026-02-03T00:03:48.478623+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;December 2014&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;I've read Villehardouin's chronicle of the Fourth Crusade at least
two times, maybe three.  And yet if I had to write down everything
I remember from it, I doubt it would amount to much more than a
page.  Multiply this times several hundred, and I get an uneasy
feeling when I look at my bookshelves. What use is it to read all
these books if I remember so little from them?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A few months ago, as I was reading Constance Reid's excellent
b&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//know.html"/>
    <published>2014-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//pinch.html</id>
    <title>The Fatal Pinch</title>
    <updated>2026-02-03T00:03:48.476181+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;December 2014&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Many startups go through a point a few months before they die where
although they have a significant amount of money in the bank, they're
also losing a lot each month, and revenue growth is either nonexistent
or mediocre.  The company has, say, 6 months of runway.  Or to put
it more brutally, 6 months before they're out of business.  They
expect to avoid that by raising more from investors.
&lt;font color="#999999"&gt;[&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//pinch.html"/>
    <published>2014-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//mean.html</id>
    <title>Mean People Fail</title>
    <updated>2026-02-03T00:03:48.474209+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;November 2014&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;It struck me recently how few of the most successful people I know
are mean.  There are exceptions, but remarkably few.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Meanness isn't rare.  In fact, one of the things the internet has
shown us is how mean people can be.  A few decades ago, only famous
people and professional writers got to publish their opinions.  Now
everyone can, and we can all see the long tail of
meanness that had previously been hidden.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;And yet while t&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//mean.html"/>
    <published>2014-11-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//before.html</id>
    <title>Before the Startup</title>
    <updated>2026-02-03T00:03:48.468277+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;&lt;table cellspacing="0" width="100%"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td bgcolor="#ff9922"&gt;&lt;img height="15" src="http://www.virtumundo.com/images/spacer.gif" width="1"/&gt;&lt;font size="2"&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Want to start a startup?&lt;/b&gt;  Get funded by
&lt;a href="http://ycombinator.com/apply.html"&gt;Y Combinator&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/font&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;img height="5" src="http://www.virtumundo.com/images/spacer.gif" width="1"/&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
October 2014&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;i&gt;(This essay is derived from a guest lecture in Sam Altman's &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//before.html"/>
    <published>2014-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
