<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <id>https://enigma.github.io/pgrss/rss.xml</id>
  <title>Paul Graham's Essays</title>
  <updated>2025-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <link href="https://paulgraham.com/" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://enigma.github.io/pgrss/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
  <link href="https://enigma.github.io/pgrss/rss-2004-11.xml" rel="first" type="application/rss+xml"/>
  <link href="https://enigma.github.io/pgrss/rss-2022-11.xml" rel="previous" type="application/rss+xml"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="1.0.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <subtitle>Paul Graham's Essays</subtitle>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//field.html</id>
    <title>The Shape of the Essay Field</title>
    <updated>2025-09-20T06:00:56.623083+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;June 2025&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;An essay has to tell people something they don't already know. But
there are three different reasons people might not know something,
and they yield three very different kinds of essays.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;One reason people won't know something is if it's not important to
know. That doesn't mean it will make a bad essay. For example, you
might write a good essay about a particular model of car. Readers
would learn something from it. It would add to their pi&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//field.html"/>
    <published>2025-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//goodwriting.html</id>
    <title>Good Writing</title>
    <updated>2025-09-20T06:00:56.621006+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;May 2025&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There are two senses in which writing can be good: it can&#13;
sound good, and the ideas can be right. It can have nice,&#13;
flowing sentences, and it can draw correct conclusions&#13;
about important things. It might seem as if these two&#13;
kinds of good would be unrelated, like the speed of a car&#13;
and the color it's painted. And yet I don't think they&#13;
are. I think writing that sounds good is more likely to&#13;
be right.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;So here we have the most excitin&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//goodwriting.html"/>
    <published>2025-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//do.html</id>
    <title>What to Do</title>
    <updated>2025-09-20T06:00:56.619151+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;March 2025&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;What should one do? That may seem a strange question, but it's not
meaningless or unanswerable. It's the sort of question kids ask
before they learn not to ask big questions. I only came across it
myself in the process of investigating something else. But once I
did, I thought I should at least try to answer it.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;So what &lt;i&gt;should&lt;/i&gt; one do? One should help people, and take care of
the world. Those two are obvious. But is there anything &lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//do.html"/>
    <published>2025-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//woke.html</id>
    <title>The Origins of Wokeness</title>
    <updated>2025-09-20T06:00:56.612185+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;January 2025&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The word "prig" isn't very common now, but if you look up
the definition, it will sound familiar. Google's isn't bad:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  A self-righteously moralistic person who behaves as if
  superior to others.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
This sense of the word originated in the 18th century, and
its age is an important clue: it shows that although
wokeness is a comparatively recent phenomenon, it's an
instance of a much older one.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There's a certain &lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//woke.html"/>
    <published>2025-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//writes.html</id>
    <title>Writes and Write-Nots</title>
    <updated>2025-09-20T06:00:56.611209+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;October 2024&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;I'm usually reluctant to make predictions about technology, but I
feel fairly confident about this one: in a couple decades there
won't be many people who can write.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;One of the strangest things you learn if you're a writer is how
many people have trouble writing. Doctors know how many people have
a mole they're worried about; people who are good at setting up
computers know how many people aren't; writers know how many people
need help&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//writes.html"/>
    <published>2024-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//when.html</id>
    <title>When To Do What You Love</title>
    <updated>2025-09-20T06:00:56.609165+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;September 2024&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There's some debate about whether it's a good idea to "follow your
passion." In fact the question is impossible to answer with a simple
yes or no. Sometimes you should and sometimes you shouldn't, but
the border between should and shouldn't is very complicated. The
only way to give a general answer is to trace it.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;When people talk about this question, there's always an implicit
"instead of." All other things being equal, why wouldn't&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//when.html"/>
    <published>2024-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//foundermode.html</id>
    <title>Founder Mode</title>
    <updated>2025-09-20T06:00:56.607511+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;September 2024&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;At a YC event last week Brian Chesky gave a talk that everyone who
was there will remember. Most founders I talked to afterward said
it was the best they'd ever heard. Ron Conway, for the first time
in his life, forgot to take notes. I'm not going to try to reproduce
it here. Instead I want to talk about a question it raised.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The theme of Brian's talk was that the conventional wisdom about
how to run larger companies is mistaken. As &lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//foundermode.html"/>
    <published>2024-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//persistence.html</id>
    <title>The Right Kind of Stubborn</title>
    <updated>2025-09-20T06:00:56.604511+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;July 2024&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Successful people tend to be persistent. New ideas often don't work
at first, but they're not deterred. They keep trying and eventually
find something that does.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Mere obstinacy, on the other hand, is a recipe for failure. Obstinate
people are so annoying. They won't listen. They beat their heads
against a wall and get nowhere.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;But is there any real difference between these two cases? Are
persistent and obstinate people actually b&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//persistence.html"/>
    <published>2024-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//reddits.html</id>
    <title>The Reddits</title>
    <updated>2025-09-20T06:00:56.603515+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;March 2024&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;I met the Reddits before we even started Y Combinator. In fact they
were one of the reasons we started it.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;YC grew out of a talk I gave to the Harvard Computer Society (the
undergrad computer club) about how to start a startup. Everyone
else in the audience was probably local, but Steve and Alexis came
up on the train from the University of Virginia, where they were
seniors. Since they'd come so far I agreed to meet them for coffee.
They&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//reddits.html"/>
    <published>2024-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//google.html</id>
    <title>How to Start Google</title>
    <updated>2025-09-20T06:00:56.600876+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;March 2024&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;i&gt;(This is a talk I gave to 14 and 15 year olds about what to do now
if they might want to start a startup later. Lots of schools think
they should tell students something about startups. This is what I
think they should tell them.)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Most of you probably think that when you're released into the
so-called real world you'll eventually have to get some kind of
job. That's not true, and today I'm going to talk about a trick you
can use t&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//google.html"/>
    <published>2024-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//best.html</id>
    <title>The Best Essay</title>
    <updated>2025-09-20T06:00:56.595407+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;March 2024&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Despite its title this isn't meant to be the best essay. My goal
here is to figure out what the best essay would be like.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;It would be well-written, but you can write well about any topic.
What made it special would be what it was about.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Obviously some topics would be better than others. It probably
wouldn't be about this year's lipstick colors. But it wouldn't be
vaporous talk about elevated themes either. A good essay has to be&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//best.html"/>
    <published>2024-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//superlinear.html</id>
    <title>Superlinear Returns</title>
    <updated>2025-09-20T06:00:56.590158+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;October 2023&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;One of the most important things I didn't understand about the world
when I was a child is the degree to which the returns for performance
are superlinear.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Teachers and coaches implicitly told us the returns were linear.
"You get out," I heard a thousand times, "what you put in." They
meant well, but this is rarely true. If your product is only half
as good as your competitor's, you don't get half as many customers.
You get no customer&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//superlinear.html"/>
    <published>2023-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//greatwork.html</id>
    <title>How to Do Great Work</title>
    <updated>2025-09-20T06:00:56.575846+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;July 2023&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If you collected lists of techniques for doing great work in a lot
of different fields, what would the intersection look like? I decided
to find out by making it.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Partly my goal was to create a guide that could be used by someone
working in any field. But I was also curious about the shape of the
intersection. And one thing this exercise shows is that it does
have a definite shape; it's not just a point labelled "work hard."&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The &lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//greatwork.html"/>
    <published>2023-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://paulgraham.com//getideas.html</id>
    <title>How to Get New Ideas</title>
    <updated>2025-09-20T06:00:56.575077+00:00</updated>
    <content>&lt;font face="verdana" size="2"&gt;January 2023&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;i&gt;(&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/stef/status/1617222428727586816"&gt;&lt;u&gt;Someone&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; fed my essays into GPT to make something that could answer
questions based on them, then asked it where good ideas come from.  The
answer was ok, but not what I would have said. This is what I would have said.)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The way to get new ideas is to notice anomalies: what seems strange,
or missing, or broken? You can see anomalies in everyday life (much
of&lt;/font&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://paulgraham.com//getideas.html"/>
    <published>2023-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>
